Finding Aid for Ronald Freedman papers, 1961-2000.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ronald Freedman papers 1961-2000
Freedman, Ronald 1917-
0490 Aa 2
Professor of sociology and director of the Population Studies Center at the University of Michigan, Ronald Freedman's research interests centered on population structure and social change. Freedman's papers consist of documentation from two large-scale survey analysis projects he was involved with, including survey questionnaires, data, and reports from Taiwan Population Studies, and Detroit Area Studies.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received through the Institute for Social Research (donor number: 3563 ) in October 2003.
The collection is open for research.
Born August 8, 1917, in Winnipeg, Manitoba, Canada, Ronald Freedman obtained an A.B. degree in 1939, and an M.S. degree in 1940, both from the University of Michigan. He joined the University of Michigan faculty in 1946, after he received his Ph.D. degree at the University of Chicago. He was appointed assistant professor in 1949, associate professor in 1953, and professor in 1957. In 1979, he was named as the Roderick D. McKenzie Distinguished Professor of Sociology. He also served as director of the Population Studies Center within the Institute for Social Research, president of the Population Association of America, and a member of the National Academy of Sciences.
Freedman's scholarly interests focused on issues of population structure and social change. In the early 1950s, he pioneered the use of surveys both to monitor current fertility trends and to estimate future changes in birth rates. He was among the first to rigorously analyze fertility patterns in developing countries. His early work in Taiwan demonstrated the feasibility of using surveys to determine the causes of changes in birth rates and the future course of such rates.
In the 1950s Freedman helped establish the Detroit Area Study (DAS), which continues to analyze social trends in this area. In the 1960s, he established the Population Studies Center, supervising its development as it became the nation's leading institute for the training of demographers and the study of population trends.
This collection documents only a fragment of Ronald Freedman's 40-year career as a teacher and a scholar at the University of Michigan. It contains materials related to two of his most notable studies, fertility practice and attitudes in Taiwan, and family growth in the Detroit area. The collection is divided into three series: Taiwan Population Studies: Knowledge, Attitudes and Practice (KAP), Taiwan Population Studies Working Papers, and Detroit Area Studies.
Subjects:
Freedman, Ronald, 1917-2007; Population research.; Demography--Methodology.; Birth control--Taiwan.; University of Michigan. Detroit Area Study.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Population Studies Center.
- Taiwan Population Studies: Knowledge, Attitudes and Practice (KAP)
  The first series, Taiwan Population Studies: Knowledge, Attitudes and Practice (KAP) (1964-2000, 1.2 linear feet), consists of questionnaire, codes, tables, reports, correspondence and memos from a series of surveys and follow-ups conducted in Taiwan on fertility practices and attitudes. The records contain comprehensive information about the mechanics of the study, such as construction of the survey, coding of the raw data, and analysis of the data in tables. The early phases of the study, KAP I to KAP V, are well documented in correspondence, memos and reports. KAP VIII contains only fragments of raw data. The first three surveys and follow-ups focus mainly on attitudes and practice of Intra-Uterine Device (IUD) acceptors in Taiwan and is also referred to as IUD I, IUD II, and IUD III. The later surveys expand to more general family and fertility study. The series is organized by each of the KAP studies: KAP I, KAP II, KAP III, KAP IV, KAP V, KAP VIII according to different surveys and follow-ups conducted over the years.
  KAP I consists of materials for the first province-wide fertility survey in 1965 (also referred to as IUD I), including codes and questionnaire and tables of data. KAP II consists of materials from the second province-wide fertility survey in 1967 (also referred to as IUD II), including tables of data, codes, questionnaires, memos, correspondence, and reports.
  KAP III documentation is comprised of materials from the 1969 third IUD follow-up survey, including codes and questionnaire, tables, reports, memos and correspondence. It also includes reports and papers prepared for the Population Council's Country Review on the Taiwan program and materials related to the Muller Economic Project, another survey on family economic conditions conducted in Taiwan and referred to in KAP III.
  KAP IV contains materials from the 1973 fourth family and fertility survey, including codes and questionnaires, tables, reports and papers, memos and correspondence. KAP V consists of codes, tables and results from the fifth Taiwan family and fertility survey. KAP VIII material consists of tables from a working paper and limited correspondence discussing KAP VIII data.
  - KAP I (Box 1)
    - Codes and Questionnaire 1964-1967 (Box 1)
    - Tables: Calculation of Mean First Birth Interval 1964-1967 (Box 1)
  - KAP II
    - Codes, Questionnaire and Plans 1967-1969 (Box 1)
    - Topic: Family and Household study 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Memos and Correspondence 1966-1967 (Box 1)
    - Reports 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - KAP III
    - Population Council Country Review: Taiwan 1970 (Box 1)
    - Codes and Questionnaire 1969-1972 (Box 1)
    - Tables 1970-1973 (Box 1)
    - Muller Economic Project 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Reports 1969-1972 (Box 1)
    - Memos and Correspondence 1969-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - KAP IV
    - Codes and Questionnaire 1975-1979, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Tables 1974-1980 (Box 1)
    - Reports and Papers 1972-1978 (Box 1)
    - Memos and Correspondence 1971-1979 (Box 1)
  - KAP V
    - Codes 1979-1982 (Box 1)
    - Tables 1981-1984 (Box 2)
    - Results and Notes 1980-1984 (Box 2)
  - KAP VIII
    - Tables, ca. 1995-2000 (Box 2)
    - Paper 1999 (Box 2)
- Taiwan Population Studies Working Papers
  The Taiwan Population Studies Working Papers (1969-1980, 0.4 linear feet) series is a set of papers issued in multilithed form and numbered from 1 to 45. The papers date from 1969 to 1980. Some of the papers were later published. The papers deal with various aspects of populations trends and family planning in Taiwan. The studies are based on the collaborative work between the University of Michigan Population Studies Center and the Taiwan Institute of Family Planning. Freedman is the author or co-author of many of the working papers, although several different authors are represented.
  - Papers 1-45 1969-1980, 4 folders (Box 2)
- Detroit Area Studies (DAS)
  The Detroit Area Studies (DAS) (1961-1999, 0.4 linear feet) series contains materials related to a 15-year longitudinal study on factors affecting family size in the Detroit area, especially the relationship between economic status and patterns of family growth. The project plans and proposals give a good overview of the objectives of the study, and the methodology of the study is well documented in papers. However, the coverage of mechanics such as coding and tables of data is partial and incomplete. The series consists of questionnaires, codes, tables, instruction books for interviewers, research proposal, project plans and reports, memos and correspondence from the different phases of the study. It is further divided by study: DAS I, DAS II, and DAS General according to the research time span.
  DAS I, consists of materials from the survey Family Growth in Detroit and its follow-ups from 1962 to 1969, including codes and questionnaires, instruction books for the interviewers and papers concerning the methodology of the research. DAS II, consists of codes, questionnaire and tables from the 1977 study: 1977 Family Growth in Detroit. DAS General includes a research proposal, project plans and reports, correspondence and memos that span the whole DAS program.
  - DAS I
    - Codes for Project #952 (Third Follow-up Survey) 1966 (Box 2)
    - Questionnaires 1962-1966 (Box 2)
    - Instruction Books for Interviewers 1962-1966 (Box 2)
    - Methodology Papers 1967-1969 (Box 2)
  - DAS II
    - Questionnaire 1977 (Box 2)
    - Table Updates for Pre-Marital Pregnancy (PMP) Articles 1977 (Box 2)
    - Tables 1977 (Box 2)
    - Codes 1977 (Box 2)
  - DAS General
    - Proposal, Plans and Reports 1961-1978 (Box 2)
    - Memos and Correspondence 1966-1999 (Box 2)